<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dominium maris: or, The dominion of the sea. Expressing the title, which the Venetians pretend unto the sole dominion, and absolute sovereigntie of the Adriatick Sea, commonly called the gulph of Venice. Manifested in a pleading, or argument, betwixt the Republick of Venice and the Emperor Ferdinand. Whereby is sufficiently proved, that the sea as well as the land, is liable to the laws of proprietie, and may bee brought under the jurisdiction and protection of particular princes and states. Contrarie to the assertion of those, who affirm, the sea to bee free, and under the dominion of no man. Translated out of Italian.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81609</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866395</idno>
  <idno type="VID">118667</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240960813</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E795_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207338</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866395</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866395e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81609)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118667)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 121:E795[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dominium maris: or, The dominion of the sea. Expressing the title, which the Venetians pretend unto the sole dominion, and absolute sovereigntie of the Adriatick Sea, commonly called the gulph of Venice. Manifested in a pleading, or argument, betwixt the Republick of Venice and the Emperor Ferdinand. Whereby is sufficiently proved, that the sea as well as the land, is liable to the laws of proprietie, and may bee brought under the jurisdiction and protection of particular princes and states. Contrarie to the assertion of those, who affirm, the sea to bee free, and under the dominion of no man. Translated out of Italian.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Du Gard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom 1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Maritime law --  Italy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sovereignty --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118667:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dominium Maris:</hi> OR, THE DOMINION OF THE SEA.</p>
            <p>Expressing the Title, which the <hi>Venetians</hi> pretend unto the sole dominion, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Sovereigntie of the <hi>Adriatick Sea,</hi> commonly called <hi>The Gulph of Venice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Manifested in a Pleading, or Argument, betwixt the Republick of <hi>Venice</hi> and the Emperor <hi>Ferdinand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby is sufficiently proved, That the Sea as well as the Land, is liable to the Laws of Proprietie, and may bee brought under the jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and protection of particular Princes and States. Contrarie to the assertion of those, who affirm, the Sea to bee free, and under the dominion of no man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Translated out of Italian.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Du Gard. An. Dom.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118667:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118667:2"/>
            <head>An Advertisement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               <hi>Thought it fitting not to instruct, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to remember the Reader, that this Sea, over which the</hi> Venetians <hi>challenge Sovereigntie and Dominion, beeing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the</hi> Gulph, <hi>is nothing els but a large bay or inlet of the sea, which entering in betwixt two lands; and severing them for manie miles continuance, in the end receiv's a stop or interruption of further passage, by an opposite shore, which join's both the said lands toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It is called the</hi> Gulph of Venice, <hi>from the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of</hi> Venice, <hi>situated upon certain broken Islands near unto the bottom thereof. It is also called the</hi> Adriatick Sea, <hi>from the antient citie of</hi> Adria, <hi>lying not far distant from the former. From the entrance thereof unto the bottom, it contein's in length about 600 Italian miles: where it is broadest it is 160 miles ever, in others but 80, in the most 100. The south<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>west shore of it is bounded by the Provinces of</hi> Pugha, <hi>and</hi> Abruzzo <hi>in the kingdom of</hi> Naples, <hi>the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisate of</hi> Ancona <hi>and</hi> Romagnia <hi>in the Pope's State,
<pb facs="tcp:118667:3"/> and the Marquisate of</hi> Trevisana <hi>in the</hi> Venetian <hi>State. The North part of it, or bottom, hath</hi> Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uli <hi>for its bounds, the North-East is limited by</hi> Istria, Dalmatia, Albania, <hi>and</hi> Epirus: <hi>whereof</hi> Istria <hi>doth not so entirely belong unto the</hi> Venetians, <hi>but that the Arch-Duke of</hi> Gratz <hi>of the Austrian family, who at this present is Emperor, doth possess divers Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritim towns therein. In</hi> Dalmatia, <hi>saving</hi> Zura, Spalato, <hi>and</hi> Cattaro, <hi>they have nothing of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the rest belonging to the Republick of</hi> Ragusa, <hi>and to the Turks. In</hi> Albania <hi>and</hi> Epirus, <hi>they pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess nothing at all, it beeing entirely the Turk's. So that hee, who shall examine the circuit of this sea, which must contain above 1200 miles, shall finde the shores of the</hi> Venetian <hi>signorie, not to take up intire 200 of them, omitting som scatter'd towns and dispersed Islands, lying on the Turkish side of the Adriatick shore. For the securing hereof from the depredation of Pirates, and the pretenses of divers Potent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as the Pope, Emperor, King of</hi> Spain, <hi>and the great Turk; who have each of them large territories lying thereupon, also to caus all such ships, as navigate the same, to go to</hi> Venice, <hi>and there to pay custom and other duties, the Republick maintain's continually in action a great number of ships, gallies and galliots,
<pb facs="tcp:118667:3"/> whereto they also add more, as there may bee occasion, whereof som lie about the bottom of the Gulph in</hi> Istria, <hi>others about the Islands of</hi> Dalmatia, <hi>to clear those parts of Pirates, who have much infested those seas: others, and those of most force, have their stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Island of</hi> Corfu, <hi>and in that of</hi> Candie: <hi>in the first of which commonly reside's the Captain of the Gulph, whom they call by the name of</hi> Proveditor, <hi>or</hi> Provisor general, <hi>whose office it is to secure the Navigation of the Gulph not onely from the</hi> Corsari <hi>or Pirates, but to provide that neither the gallies nor ships of the Pope, the King of</hi> Spain, <hi>or great Turk, do so much as enter the same, without permission of the Signorie, or Republick, and upon such conditions as best pleaseth them; which they are so careful to effect, as in the year 1638 the Turkish fleet entring the Gulph without licens, was assailed by the Venetian General, who sunk divers of their vessels, and compelling the rest to flie unto</hi> Valona, <hi>hee held them there besieged, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the same citie, and Port whereon it stand's, bee under the jurisdiction of the Grand Signor And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding that a great and dangerous war was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ensue thereupon, betwixt the Grand-Signor and the Republick, becaus the Venetian General, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not content to have chaced them into their own
<pb facs="tcp:118667:4"/> Ports, did moreover then that, sink their vessels, &amp; land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his men, slew divers of their mariners who had esca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his furie at sea: yet after that a very honorable peace was again concluded betwixt them, wherein, amongst other things, it was agreed, that it should bee lawful for the</hi> Venetians, <hi>as often as any Turkish vessels did without their licence enter the Gulph, to seiz upon them by force, if they would not otherwise obey. And that it should likewise bee lawful for them so to do, within any haven, or under any fort of the Grand-Signor's, bordering on any part of the Venetian Gulph. Out of all which, when I considered the real and absolute sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigntie, which this Republick doth actually enjoy over this sea, which they have ever defended, as well by the sword as the pen; and withal how that som neighbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nations of late years, did seem to envie the title of</hi> England <hi>to the narrow seas, affirming in som of their writings, the</hi> Sea to bee free; <hi>that</hi> it neither ought, nor could bee under the jurisdiction of any; <hi>that</hi> it was a wilde beast which could not bee ruled; <hi>that,</hi> possessio <hi>beeing</hi> Pedis positio, <hi>there</hi> could no possession bee either taken or kept of it; <hi>that</hi> the limits thereof, beeing a fluent element, could not bee scored out, <hi>or</hi> certainly determined; <hi>that</hi> it was as free for all mankinde to use, &amp; as common as the
<pb facs="tcp:118667:4"/> aër, <hi>with many other things to that purpose; I chancing som years past to bee at</hi> Venice, <hi>upon consideration of the premisses, did labor with a great desire, to know the grounds of that title, whereupon the</hi> Venetians <hi>found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their</hi> Dominion of the sea; <hi>and after much search, even to the despair of obteining of it, I happened upon this ensuing argument, containing a</hi> Plea <hi>or</hi> Dispute, <hi>betwixt the</hi> Austrians <hi>and</hi> Venetians, <hi>touching the</hi> Dominion of the Adriatick Sea, <hi>not fictitious or devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed onely to color the caus, but faithfully transcribed from out the publick Registers of that citie, which I offer herewith to the Reader in English, and withall these two considerations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, <hi>that hereby it will appear, that the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of</hi> England'<hi>s challenge to the dominion of the sea, is neither a Noveltie or singularitie; especially, when it is besides most apparant that the King of</hi> Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, <hi>doth not onely pretend to the Sovereigntie of the Sound, but causeth all such ships as pass through it, to pay what toll hee pleaseth. The great Turk prohibit's all Nations, saving his own vassals, to enter the black sea, or</hi> Pontus Euxinus; <hi>the like hee doth to the red sea, which contein's at the least 1200 miles in length, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning from the streits of</hi> Babelmondel, <hi>which give's entrance thereinto, and ending at the tower of</hi> Sues,
<pb facs="tcp:118667:5"/>
               <hi>which is seated at the bottom thereof. The King of</hi> Portugal <hi>opposeth to the utmost of his power, any, but his own subjects to sail into the East Indies, affirming those seas to bee intirely under his dominion, as well by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, as the Pope's donation, insomuch, as the smallest vessel, even of the natives of those parts, cannot sail from port to port, without the passport of the</hi> Vice-Roy of Goa, <hi>or of som other by him deputed thereto, styling himself, amongst other his titles, to bee King of the conquest, navigation, and commerce, or traffick of</hi> Aethiopia, Arabia, Persia, India, <hi>&amp;c. which hath been hitherto so punctually observed, as no</hi> Casti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, <hi>or Spaniard, might at any time, or for any occasion, sail into the East Indies, though both those Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were for many years together united under one King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>if the Dominion of these seas do truely and properly belong to the Commonwealth of</hi> England <hi>(as hath been so sufficiently cleared and proved to the whole world, by that learned book entituled</hi> Mare Clausum) <hi>why may not, or ought not the People of</hi> England, <hi>by all lawful waies procure, that the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of these Seas that so justly appertein's unto them, may be secured from any force, violence, or opposition, how great soever, of their most powerful neighbors;
<pb facs="tcp:118667:5"/> whenas wee see the</hi> Venetians <hi>to bee so jealous in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of the title they pretend to their Seas, as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to suffer it to bee in the least sort questioned, they do upon all occasions oppose themselvs by force, or otherwise, against the most potent Princes of</hi> Europe <hi>and</hi> Asia. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>CLAREAMONTOS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:118667:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118667:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Dominium Maris:</hi> Or, The Dominion of the Sea.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter a long peace, betwixt the progenitors of the Emperor <hi>Maximilian</hi> the first, and the Republick of <hi>Venice,</hi> in the year 1508, there began certain slight differences, which concluded in a notable, and most memorable war: insomuch as the Republick, for 22 years following, were with the said Prince, and with his posteritie, for divers respects, som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in war, somtimes in peace, and somtimes in truce, until in the year 1529 all differences betwixt them were composed, and a peace concluded in <hi>Bolonia,</hi> which continued all that age, with the Emperor <hi>Charls</hi> the fifth, together with his brother <hi>Ferdinando</hi> King of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and Archduke of <hi>Austria.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus by the division, made betwixt the said brethren, seven years before, all the <hi>Austrian</hi> lands which confined with the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians,</hi> were laid by agreement unto the part which belonged unto King <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> the confines of which as they had conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture with the lands of the Republick, were very intricate; and of great difficultie to conclude, unto whether partie they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118667:7"/> as well for the publick reasons of the said Princes, as for those of their private subjects; To end all which in quiet, it was agreed that there should bee an arbitrarie Tribunal erected in <hi>Trent,</hi> for the deciding of these doubts, which in the year 1535, pronounced sentence, whereby all the differences (beeing more then an hundred) were definitively concluded.</p>
            <p>Here notwithstanding the difficultie ceased not, becaus som did travers the execution of the sentence, so, as in progress of time, new quarrels did arise from both sides, each one pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new wrongs offered by the advers partie. Whereupon to put an end to all these differences, there was by the common consent, as well of <hi>Ferdinando</hi> (who succeeded in the Empire by the resignation of his brother) as of the Republick, a convention appointed in <hi>Friuli</hi> 1563, of five Commissaries, one Procurator, and three Advocates, for each part, who should treat of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, as well old as new, and should have power to conclude them, under the ratification of the several Princes. And this so great a number of Judges, was desired by the Emperor, the better to give satisfaction to his subjects, of several provinces, interessed in the caus.</p>
            <p>Of the Imperial side, the Commissaries were <hi>Andrew Preghel</hi> a Baron of Austria, <hi>Maximilian Dorimbergh, Elenger de Goritia, Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen Sourz,</hi> and <hi>Anthonie Statemberger:</hi> the Procurator was, <hi>Gia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>como Campana,</hi> Chancellor of <hi>Goritia:</hi> the Doctors or Advocates were <hi>Andrea Rapicio, Gervasio Alberto,</hi> and <hi>Giovan Maria Gratia Dei.</hi> For the Venetians the Commissaries were, <hi>Sebastian Venier, Marino de Cavalli, Pietro Sanudo, Giovan Baptista Contarini,</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin Barbarigo:</hi> The Procurator was, <hi>Giovan Antonio</hi> a secretarie: the Advocates <hi>Marquardo Susanna, Francesco Gratiano,</hi> and <hi>Giacomo Chizzola.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this Convention the complaints on both sides were opened,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118667:7"/> which beeing argued, and the other publick differences partly composed, and partly decided, there was taken into considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a Petition of the Imperial Procurator, in this form, <hi>Ejusdem Majestatis nomine requiritur, ut posthac illius subditis, atque aliis in sinu Adriatico tutò navigare, ac negotiari liceat. Item ut damna, Tergestinis Mercatoribus at que aliis illata, restituantur.</hi> It is required in the name of his Majestie, that hereafter it may be lawful for his subjects, and others, to traffick and navigate safely in the Adriatick Gulph. Likewise that recompence bee made for the damages susteined by the merchants of <hi>Trieste,</hi> and others. And <hi>Rapicio</hi> the advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate did accompanie this demand with saying; that <hi>this was not a caus to bee handled with any subtiltie, it beeing a thing most notorious, that navigation ought to bee free, notwithstanding the subjects of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stìe had been constrained to go with their ships to</hi> Venice, <hi>and there to pay custom, at which his Majestìe was aggrieved, and made instance that it might bee remedied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this <hi>Chizzola</hi> Advocate of the Republick made answer, saying, that it was a clear case indeed, that Navigation ought to bee free, but yet those things, whereat they were aggrieved, were no waies repugnant to this freedom; forasmuch as in countries which are most free, those who have the dominion thereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv <hi>custom,</hi> and order by which way all merchandise shall pass; and therefore no bodie should bee grieved, if the <hi>Venetians,</hi> for their own respects, did use so to do in the Adriatick Sea, which is under their dominion; and hee added, that if they intended to dispute of the business in question, hee was to advertise them, that this caus could not by any pretens bee brought into judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at that convention, which was onely instituted, for the execution of such things as were formerly sentenced and for righting of such new wrongs, which succeeded after the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; it beeing besides a thing most notorious, that the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118667:8"/> as Lord of the Adriatick Sea, did exercise that dominion at the present, which from time out of minde, it had alwaies don, without any interruption, as well in receiving of customs, as in assigning of places for the exaction of it, and that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens now alleged was new, and never before used by any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessor of the Emperor, either as King of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> or as Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke of <hi>Austria,</hi> or the countries thereto adjacent, or of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie then being, for many years, until this present time. Hee chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged the Imperialists to shew, when ever any such thing was before pretended; certainly not before the peace of <hi>Bolonia;</hi> for then such a difference as this (if there had been any such) had been there determined, or referred over to the Arbitrarie Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, wherein were handled above 120 controversies, but of this not any mention made, neither, from that time to this, was there any such pretension once set a foot. But if this were a new wrong, succeeding after the sentence of <hi>Trent,</hi> they should shew what it was, and when it had beginning, becaus hee was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to shew unto them, that any thing concerning the same, was of most ancient use and continuance, without the least no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veltie in the world; and therefore they ought not to bee heard, who came with demands, which could take no original either from the sentence of <hi>Trent,</hi> or from any innovation of wrongs succeeding thereupon.</p>
            <p>To this <hi>Rapicio</hi> replied, thathee intended not to lay his principal foundation upon that, which to all is so well known, which is to say, <hi>that the Sea is common and free,</hi> and that by reason thereof, not any might bee prohibited, to sail unto any place, which best pleased him: and if any Doctors should happen to say, that the Republick hath a prescript dominion over the Adriatick Sea, with a long possession, notwithstanding they prove it not: and to Doctors who affirm a thing barely out of fact, without any
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118667:8"/> manner of proof, little belief is to bee given; for which caus, hee would not dwell upon that, but would com to his principal reason, which was, that admitting the Republick to bee Patron of the Sea, yet the Emperor's subjects might navigate freely by the capitulations, which were established betwixt the Princes on both sides, and therefore the Petition proposed was pertinent to bee handled by the said Convention; to which (hee beeing so required by the <hi>Venetians)</hi> added this for a foundation, <hi>Quia li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera navigatio Maris Adriatìcî cùm Majestatis suae Caesareae, tum subdito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum damno &amp; incommodo, ab Illustrissimi Domini Veneti triremium Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectis impedita fuerit, contra Capitula Vormatiae, Bononiae, Andegavi, &amp; Venetiis inita:</hi> Forasmuch as the free navigation of the Adriatick Sea, hath been hindred by the Captains of the Venetian's Gallies, to the loss and prejudice of his Imperial Majestie, and of his subjects, against the Capitulations of <hi>Worms, Bolonia, Angiers,</hi> and <hi>Venice.</hi> And here hee produced a passage of the Capitulation of <hi>Bolonia</hi> which spake as followeth; <hi>Quod communes subditi liberè, tutè, &amp; securè possint in utriusque statibus &amp; dominiis tam terrâ, quàm Mari, morarì &amp; negotiari cum bonis suìs, ac si essent incolae, &amp; subditi il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Principis, ac Dominii, cujus patrias, &amp; Dominia adibunt; provìdia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>túrque, nè vis aut aliqua injuria, ulla de causa, eis inferatur, celeritérque jus administretur.</hi> That the subjects of either partie may freely, safely, and securely abide, and traffick with their goods, in the States and Dominions of one another, in like manner as if they were inhabitants, and subjects of that Prince and State, into whose countrie or Dominion they do com: and that it bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that no violence or injurie, bee for any caus whatsoêver offered them, and moreover that justice be speedily administred. Hee also recited the capitulations of the truce of <hi>Angiers</hi> and <hi>Worms,</hi> and of the peace of <hi>Venice,</hi> which is not necessarie here to repeat, beeing of the same tenor. Hee did rest much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118667:9"/> the word <hi>liberè,</hi> considering that <hi>liberè</hi> is joined to the word <hi>Navigare:</hi> by which it ought to bee understood, according to the common construction of law, <hi>that everie one might navigate freely;</hi> but hee cannot bee said to bee <hi>free,</hi> who is constrained to go to <hi>Venice.</hi> Hee added moreover, that the word <hi>liberè</hi> could not bee imagined to bee superfluous, but must of necessitie ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate somthing; that the two words, <hi>tutè &amp; securè,</hi> could im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port nothing els, but without impediment, or molestation, or paying of customs; to this hee added, that there were then 400 complaints of his Majestie's subjects, whose vessels were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to go to <hi>Venice,</hi> and there made to pay custom, for happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely to arrive in the ports of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> either by fortune or som other occasion. Hee read the sentence of a Rector of <hi>Liesina,</hi> who freed a ship, which touched upon that Island by chance; and hee made a narration, that certain barks with salt were suffred, by the Venetian fleet, to pass upon their voiage, without sending them to <hi>Venice.</hi> Hee concluded that his request extended to these three points. 1. That the <hi>Austrian</hi> subjects might Navigate whither it pleased them. 2. That arriving in any port of the Republick, onely <hi>per transitum,</hi> they should not pay any thing. 3. <hi>Lastly,</hi> that coming to trade in any of them, they should not pay more, then the subjects of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chizzola</hi> answered hereto, promising clearly to solv all the objections introduced by the other, so as there should not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main any place of Replie, and to shew with true and lively rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, that what was don by the ministers of the Republick in the <hi>Gulph,</hi> was don by lawful Autoritie. And reserving himself, to speak of the Dominion of the Sea afterwards, howsoever presupposing it in the first place, hee began with the Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and <hi>first</hi> hee said, that the word, <hi>liberè,</hi> was not joined
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118667:9"/> as <hi>Rapicio</hi> said, to any such word as <hi>Navigare,</hi> but to the words <hi>Morari &amp; negotiari tam terrâ, quàm Mari:</hi> and therefore by <hi>liberè</hi> is to bee understood as the common construction of Law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend's, when one doth either dwell, or do business in the hous, or land of another, that is to say, observing the laws, and pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the rights of the countrie. Hee added also, that those Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulations, betwixt the hous of <hi>Austria,</hi> and the <hi>Republick,</hi> were equally reciprocal, and not made more in favor of the <hi>Austrians</hi> in the State of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> then of the <hi>Venetians</hi> in the State of the <hi>Austrians;</hi> neither was there greater libertie granted to the Sea, then to the Land; and that the words were clear enough, which import, that the subjects on both sides might stay, trade, and merchandise, in the State of one another, as well by Land as by Sea, and bee well intreated; Insomuch as the subjects of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> were to have no less libertie in the Lands of the <hi>Austrians,</hi> then the <hi>Austrian</hi> subjects in the Sea of <hi>Venice;</hi> And that by virtue of those words, what his Majestie would have in the State of the <hi>Republick,</hi> it is fitting that hee allow to them in his own State; and if his Imperial Majestie within his own State, upon the Land, will not yield that the subjects of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick</hi> shall go which way they list, but constrain's them to pass by such places onely, where Custom is to bee paid, hee cannot with justice demand, that his subjects may pass by or through the Sea of the <hi>Republick</hi> which way they list, but ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himself, that they go that way onely, which shall best stand with the commoditie of those who have the dominion over it; and if his Majestie caus custom to bee paid, upon <hi>his</hi> Land, why may not the <hi>Venetians</hi> likewise do it, upon <hi>their</hi> Sea? Hee demanded of them, if by the Capitulation they would have it, that the Emperor was restrained, or hindred, from taking of custom? and if not, why would they have the <hi>Venetians</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118667:10"/> tied thereunto by a Capitulation, which speak's of both Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates equally with the same words? Hee shewed by a particular narration, that from the Peace of <hi>Venice</hi> 1523. until that present, the Emperor had increased his customs, to the grievance of the <hi>Venetian</hi> subjects, in victuals and merchandise, which passed from the one State unto the other; insomuch as that which formerly paied but one, was now increased in som to 16, and in others to 20. and hee instanced in iron and other commodities, which were wont to pay little or nothing, were now raised to such an excessive custom, as proved much to the damage of the <hi>Venetians;</hi> besides they were forced to pass onely by such places, where they should pay custom, out of which to pass, it was <hi>Contra banda,</hi> and their goods confiscated. And if his Majestie think's it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to do what it pleaseth within his own estate, without break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Capitulations, hee cannot think that the <hi>Venetians</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but the same, should contrarie thereunto, any waies offend. Hee added, that in every Peace established betwixt two Princes, after a war, it is necessarie that their subjects may live and trade together, not to the excluding of customs, although there bee excluded the violences, hostilities, and other impediments of trade, which were formerly used in time of war, neither is the autoritie of the one, or other Prince, thereby taken away or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained by Sea or by Land.</p>
            <p>At the force and clearness of this discours, the <hi>Austrians</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained as it were in a trance, looking one upon another, inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that <hi>Chizzola</hi> judging it not to bee necessarie to dwell lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon this, passed to the proof of the presupposed truth, viz. <hi>That the Republick had the Dominion of the Sea,</hi> and said; that the proposition was most true, that the Sea was common and free, but yet no otherwise that could bee understood, then as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly said, The high waies are common and free, by which is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118667:10"/> meant, that they cannot bee usurped by any private person, for his sole proper service, but remain to the use of every one: not therefore that they are so free, as that they should not bee under the protection and government of som Prince, and that every one might do therein licentiously, all that which it pleased him, either by right or wrong; forasmuch as such licentiousness or Anarchie is abhorred both of God and nature, as well by Sea as by Land. That the true libertie of the Sea, exclude's it not from the protection and superioritie of such as maintain it in libertie, nor from the subjection to the laws of such, as have command over it, rather necessarily it include's it. That no less the Sea, then the Land, is subject to bee divided amongst men, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to cities and Potentates, which long since was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by God from the beginning of mankinde, as a thing most natual; which was well understood by <hi>Aristotle,</hi> when hee said, that unto Sea or maritim cities, the Sea is the territorie, becaus from thence they take their sustenance and defence; a thing which cannot possibly bee, unless part of it might bee appropriated in the like manner as the Land is, which is divided betwixt cities and governments, not by equal parts, nor according to their greatness, but as they have been, or are able to rule, govern, and defend them. <hi>Berne</hi> is not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est citie of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and yet it hath as large a territorie, as all the rest of the twelv Cantons together. And the citie of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimberg</hi> is very great, and yet the territories thereof, hardly exceed the walls. And the citie of <hi>Venice</hi> for many years was known to bee without any possession at all upon the firm Land. Upon the Sea likewise, certain cities of great force and valor have possessed a large quantitie thereof, others of little force, have been contented with the next waters; neither are there want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examples of such, who notwithstanding they are Maritim,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118667:11"/> yet having fertile lands lying on the back of them, have been contented therewith, without ever attempting to gain any Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominion; Others, who beeing aw'd by their more mightie neighbors, have been constrained to forbear any such attempt; for which two causes, a citie, notwithstanding it bee Maritim, may happen to remain without any possession of the Sea.</p>
            <p>Hee added that God did institute Principalities, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinance of Justice, to the benefit of mankinde, which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie to be executed, as well by Sea as by Land. That S. Paul said, that <hi>for this caus there was due to Princes, customs and contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> that it should bee a great absurditie to praise the well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning, regulating, and defence of the Land, and to condemn that of the Sea: that if the Sea in som parts for the ampleness and extreme distance thereof from the Land, was not possible to bee governed and protected, that proceeded from a disabilitie and defect in mankinde; as also there are deserts so great upon the Land, as it is impossible to protect them; witness the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sandie parts of <hi>Africa,</hi> and the immens vastities of the new world. And as it is a gift of God; that a Land by the laws and publick power, bee ruled, protected and governed, so the same happen's to the Sea: that those were deceived by a gross equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, who said, that the Land by reason of its stabilitie might bee governed, but not the Sea, for beeing an unconstant element, no more then the aêr; forasmuch as if, by the Sea and the aêr, they intend all the parts of those fluent elements; it is a most certain thing, that they cannot bee governed, because, whilst a man serv's himself with any one part of them, the other escape's out of his power; but this chanceth also to rivers, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee reteined. But when it is said to rule over a Sea or river, it is not understood of the Element, but of the site, where they are placed. The water of the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea continually run's out of it,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118667:11"/> neither can it all bee kept in, and yet it is the same Sea, as well as the <hi>Tiber, Po,</hi> or the <hi>Rhine</hi> are the same rivers now, which they were 1000 years past. And this is that which is subject to the protection of Princes.</p>
            <p>Hee asked the <hi>Austrians</hi> if their pretens were, that the Sea should bee left without protection, so that any one might do therein well or ill, robbing, spoiling, and making of it unnavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable; this would bee so absurd, as hee durst answer for them, <hi>no:</hi> therefore hee concluded, that by a necessarie consequence his Majestie would acknowledg, that it should bee kept, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned and protected by those unto whom it did appertain by divine disposition: which if it were so, hee desired to know, if it seemed to them a just thing that such should do it, with the expence of their own pains, charges, and bloud; or rather that such should contribute towards it, who did equally enjoy the benefit: To this also hee durst answer for them, that they would say the doctrine of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Paul is too clear in the point (not to allege matter of law) that <hi>all such who are under govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and protection, are thereby bound to pay customs and contributions.</hi> And thereupon hee concluded, that if the Republick were that Prince, to whom it did appertain to govern and protect the Adriatick Sea, it followed necessarily, that whosoever Navigate's it, ought to bee subject to their laws, in the same manner as such are, who travel through a countrie upon the Land.</p>
            <p>From thence hee went on to shew, that this Dominion over the Sea, from time out of minde, did belong to the Republick, and thereupon caused to bee read out of an Abstract which hee had taken, the opinions of thirtie Lawyers, whom from the year 1300, until that present time, did speak of the Dominion which the Republick had over the Sea, as of a thing most no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, and of which, even in their times, the minde of man
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118667:12"/> knew not the contrarie: som of them affirming, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick had no less Dominion over the Sea, then over the citie of <hi>Venice;</hi> others saying, that the Adriatick Sea is the territorie and demeasnes of the said citie, making mention of the lawful power which the <hi>Venetians</hi> had to establish laws over Navigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to impose customs upon such as navigate those Seas; and hee added that hee never read any Lawyer, which ever said the contrarie. And turning himself to <hi>Rapicio</hi> hee said, that if hee would not believ those writers which testified that the Sea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> whereof they had possession from time out of minde, before the age wherein the Autors lived, although they prove it not, yet hee could not denie to receiv them for testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of such things which they saw and knew in their times, and to hold them as witnesses, far above all exception, beeing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous men, and dead so many years ago, as they could not bee any waies interessed in the present differences. And becaus more then 250 years were past, from the time that the first Autors, which hee alleged as witnesses hereof did write, to the time of those, which hee last cited in that behalf; by their attestation it was sufficiently proved, that for long time more then so many years, the Republick hath commanded the Sea, and therefore hee could not denie the immemorable possession thereof to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent.</p>
            <p>Afterwards turning himself to the Judges, hee praied them, that upon the autorities alleged, they would bee pleased to listen unto a short consideration of his, which hee did not doubt, but would leav in them a full impression of the truth. And <hi>first</hi> hee desired them to consider, that notwithstanding som of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said cited Autors speak with general words, saying, the sea of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> neither declaring the qualitie nor quantitie thereof; yet others do specifie it, using the name of the <hi>Gulph;</hi> and others with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118667:12"/> terms more expressive, saying, the <hi>Adriatick Sea;</hi> which clearly demonstrate's, not onely the site, but also the quantitie of the Sea possessed; and so shewed, that those who speak more expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively, ought to clear the passages of those, who write more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, according to the common precept, that <hi>with clear places the more obscure are to bee illustrated.</hi> Hee considered also, that the divers manner of speaking of the same Doctors, som de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving the Dominion of the Republick over the Sea, from cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom, som from prescription, others from an induced subjection, and others from a privilege, did arise all out of this reason, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause as they were most assuredly informed of the possession and jurisdiction of the said Seas, which they both saw and heard to belong to the Republick from time out of minde; so they wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon that matter, not at the instance of any one, but of their own proper motions, and by way of doctrine onely, each one of them judged it most convenient to express the title of that jurisdiction, som with one term, som with another, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out coming to use the sole true and proper term, as they would have don, if they had been put to write for the interest of any one; in which cases the Counsellors are alwaies conformable, receiving from the person interested equally the like instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>Hee added, that through the varietie of expressing themselvs, the truth of the caus was no waies diminished, but rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased; as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> saith, speaking of the diversitie which is observed to bee betwixt the holy Evangelists; because by the divers manner of expression, used by the said writers, every one may rest assured, that none of them did write <hi>nè pagato, nè pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gato,</hi> neither paied, nor praied. In which cases they are never wont to varie, from the single form prescribed unto them by the partie interessed, but rather hee that shall well examine it, shall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118667:13"/> see amongst the Doctors a wonderful concord in this one point most true, that after the declination of the Constantinopolitan Empire, the Adriatick Sea was found to bee for many years abandoned, (as also many Islands and cities of that State) in such manner, as it remained unguarded and without the protection and government of any Prince, and under the jurisdiction of no bodie, until by the <hi>Venetians,</hi> who, to receiv their livelyhood thereby, were constrained to maintain it in freedom; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon taking it into their protection, got thereby the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and dominion over it, in like manner as by the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and of Nations, the Land, the Sea, and other things, which are not under the Dominion of any other, com justly unto those who first get the possession of them; by which reason the first Empires were founded, as well upon the Land as at Sea, and daily there are new ones in the same manner formed, when any of them, either through age or vice, becoming weak, wanteth force, and sink's of it self. The which custodie and government of the Sea, so acquired, the Republick hath daily advanced, by the keeping of potent fleets and greater Armadoes every day then other, with the expence of a great deal of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and the profusion of a world of bloud, both of their Citizens and subjects, continuing without interruption, in sight of all the world, the said begun Dominion and custodie, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming and removing all such impediments, as either by Pirates or Potentates, as well of <hi>Italie</hi> as of the opposite shore, at divers times have been raised. And for the clearing of such doubts, as might arise by the subtil construction of words, hee added; that although those who took upon them to speak in the strict terms of the Law, were wont to say, that such things onely were gained by custom, which by the civil law, beeing to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, were notwithstanding converted to a private benefit, yet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118667:13"/> without any impeachment of the publick profit, as to fish in a river without impeachment of Navigation: yet for all that, the title of custom cannot bee unproperly given, where there shall bee gained and continually kept in possession and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a quantitie either of Sea or Land abandoned, and of no man possessed, as <hi>Bartholus, Baldus, Castro,</hi> and others do affirm. And although that by title of <hi>Prescription</hi> a thing cannot possible bee said to bee possessed, unless, by the occupation of it, another bee thereof spoiled and dispossessed, which title come's not in this place, forasmuch as the Republick hath not spoiled any of the possession of the Sea, but hath seized upon it, finding it abandoned and without patron or possessor: notwithstanding in som sort, it may bee called <hi>Prescription,</hi> as if a Falcon were let fly and cast off by its master, and thereupon growing wilde, should after bee taken up by another, and by him mann'd, and for a long time fed; although not properly, yet not absurdly it may bee said, that this second master hath it by <hi>Prescription.</hi> Likewise, to speak in terms of Law, the proprietie of speech doth not admit the use of this word <hi>Servitude,</hi> unless to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per territorie of a State, there bee gotten som power over ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther State, and yet State remain's patron of its own not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding; in this sens the Republick hath not brought the Sea in servitude to the citie of <hi>Venice,</hi> becaus it hath not gotten any special use or command over it, the Dominion for all that remaining to another Patron, but hath assumed the total and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Dominion thereof, which was before abandoned, neither by any governed or protected: nevertheless it may in a certain proportion bee called <hi>Servitude,</hi> inasmuch as the Republick hath been constrained to assume the total Dominion and government thereof, for the service of the citi of <hi>Venice,</hi> whereof it had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie use.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118667:14"/>
            <p>Now as touching the <hi>Privilege</hi> of keeping this Sea, and who was the Donor, this neither can here have any place, forasmuch as at the time of the assumption of it, there was not any who could make any grant thereof, the Emperor of the West never having any power or autoritie over it; and as little superioritie or jurisdiction had any other western Prince; and therefore could so much the less give it to another. The Emperor of the East, not having force sufficient to keep it, had long since aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned it, and beeing thereupon divested of all the power hee had over it, and of the possession thereof, never made any grant thereof in the successive peace and treaties which happened af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards betwixt the said Empire and the Republick. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all which, the Italian Lawyers, as professors of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarean Law, and sworn to the very words of it, beeing besides most devoted to his Imperial Majestie, as if at this present day <hi>Augustus</hi> or <hi>Antoninus</hi> did reign, do force themselves with all extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to verifieupon the Western Emperor that saying, <hi>Imperator est Dominus Mundi,</hi> The Emperor is Lord of the world. Which at that very time when it was first pronounced, was not true in the hundred part of the world, and at this present not in any considerable proportion. And whilest they would honor the Emperor, and give him, with such words as these, that which hee neither hath nor can have, they consider not the absurditie of the speech, as if they should say, that no King possessed any estate lawfully, unless it were granted him by the Emperor, which is as true, as when they affirm that the <hi>Venetians</hi> possess the Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Sea, by an Imperial privilege. But it appear's clear enough, in what sens this is spoken by them, because there is none of them do intend thereby, that there was ever any such Grant made thereof by the Emperor; but by that they do figuratively intend a privilege assumed by immemorable possession, which posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118667:14"/> they interpret to bee with the knowledg and sufferance of the Emperor, which is as much as if they should say, that Christian Kings possess their Kingdoms, and the Republick pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesseth the <hi>Adriatick Sea,</hi> as lawfully by their title of acquiring it, as if those Kingdoms and that Sea had belonged to the Emperor, and from and by him to those Princes, and to the Republick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards granted. So spaciously did <hi>Chizzola</hi> dilate in speaking of the opinion of the Lawyers, it beeing the field of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession: hee concluded, that any one might rest satisfied, as well in truth, as in reason, that by the Autoritie of the said Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, there were sure foundations laid to the caus, which hee did defend.</p>
            <p>After the testimonie of the Lawyers, hee added that of the <hi>Historians,</hi> who do relate, that the Republick, for more then 300 years past, did receiv custom, of such as sailed that Sea, and kept armed vessels in a readiness, for to compel all such ships so sail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to go to <hi>Venice,</hi> testifying moreover, that even unto their present time the same custom was observed. But upon their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testations hee dwelled not much, saying, that though they were good testimonies of preceding occurrences; yet when one go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about to prove the interests of Princes, or of private persons, hee ought to help himself by authentick writings, and to use the Historians with great discretion; som of them beeing moved by love, others with hatred, and others with hope of preferment; which constrain's them oftentimes to use flatterie, or Hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, upon which cannot bee laid any sure foundation.</p>
            <p>Wherefore hee produced an act of the general Council of Lions, <hi>anno</hi> 1274, where the Abbot of <hi>Nervesa,</hi> beeing delegated by the Pope (upon a pretension of those of <hi>Ancona</hi> to have free navigation upon the Adriatick Sea) sentenced, that the demand should bee rejected, and that the <hi>Venetians</hi> should not bee mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118667:15"/> in the defence and protection thereof, from the <hi>Sarazens</hi> and Pirates, neither should bee disturbed from exacting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon their rights and customs, which they had of victuals, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandise and other portable commodities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chizzola</hi> likewise added, that it is clean out of memorie, when first of all there was created in <hi>Venice, a Captain of the Gulph,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus in the year 1230, the Chancerie was burned, with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials of all such elections; but from that time to this present, hee could shew out of the publick Registers, the continuall suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of the said elected Captains without any interruption. Likewise hee added moreover, that there remain the Registers from that time to this, of the licences granted to pass the said Sea, with armed vessels or ships of war, and to the persons and goods belonging to their use, at the request of divers Princes, who had their possessions upon the shore of the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea, and that as well by sundrie Popes, Legates, Vicars, Governors, and Commonaltie of the Land of <hi>Romania</hi> and <hi>Marca,</hi> as by the Kings of <hi>Naples</hi> for <hi>Puglia,</hi> of which many were granted, som denied and others yielded to, but in part; But it beeing super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous to allege the Acts of those, the successors of whom do not so much as question this title, hee descended to particularize one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the predecessors of his Majestie, as Kings of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and Arch Dukes of <hi>Austria.</hi> Hee recited a Brief of Pope <hi>Urbane</hi> the sixt, directed to <hi>Antenio Veniero</hi> the Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> bearing date <hi>Luca</hi> 14 Junii 1388. where hee give's him thanks, that with his Gallies deputed for the keeping of the Gulph, <hi>Marie</hi> Queen of <hi>Hungarie</hi> had been inlarged, who had been kept prisoner in <hi>Castel-novo;</hi> with two other congratulatorie letters, the one to the said Queen, the other to King <hi>Sigismund,</hi> who after was Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, beeing her husband, rejoicing with them likewise of the said enlargement made by means of the Captain of the <hi>Venetian</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118667:15"/> Gallies, deputed to the custodie of the <hi>Gulph.</hi> Afterwards hee caused to bee read a safe Conduct granted at the Petition of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulph</hi> Earl of <hi>Sala,</hi> in the name of <hi>Ladislaus</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> and of <hi>William</hi> Arch-Duke of <hi>Austria</hi> anno 1399. 12 <hi>Decembris,</hi> that the sister of the said King (espoused to the aforenamed Arch-Duke) might bee conducted by sea from <hi>Puglia,</hi> to the coasts of her husband, with Gallies and other vessels, in all to the number of about twelv; with condition that there should not bee suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to pass upon them any <hi>Bandito</hi> or banished person of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> who had don any thing against the Republick, which did merit death: which safe-conduct should bee available to the <hi>Austrians,</hi> as well in going as in coming, so as by the same, they might also reimbark at <hi>Trieste</hi> and return unto <hi>Puglia.</hi> But yet this safe Conduct was not made use of, because the King having deferred the departure of his sister for a small time, in the <hi>interim</hi> shee died.</p>
            <p>Also hee produced two letters of the Emperor <hi>Frederick,</hi> unto Duke <hi>Giovanni Mocenigo,</hi> the first dated in <hi>Gratz</hi> 24 Sept. 1478. the other 2 Apr. 1479. from the same place, where hee tell's him that hee having taken order that there should bee brought from <hi>Puglia</hi> and <hi>Abruzzo,</hi> to his castles of <hi>Castro</hi> and of <hi>Istria,</hi> a certain quantitie of corn, hee request's that it may bee permitted him to do it freely, which beeing to him a great pleasure, hee shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg it with many thanks.</p>
            <p>This hee seconded with a letter of <hi>Beatrice</hi> Queen of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> to <hi>Giovanni Mocenigo</hi> Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> dated the last of Jan. 1481. whereby desiring for her proper use to have divers things from the parts of <hi>Italie,</hi> which shee could not bring from thence by Sea, without the permission of the Republick, shee desired that, for curtesie sake and friendship, it might bee granted her, which shee should take for a great favor, and correspond upon the like occasion.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118667:16"/>
            <p>And another of <hi>Matthias</hi> King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> to the said Duke dated 26 Febr. 1482. where relating how the Republick was accustomed to give licence every year to Count <hi>Frangipani</hi> patron of <hi>Segna</hi> and other maritim places, to bring from <hi>Puglia</hi> and <hi>Marca</hi> a certain quantitie of victuals, and that after the said places, were passed over into his hands, hee had omitted to desire it; wherefore hee now praied, that the same grace might bee shewed unto him, &amp; that concerning this, hee would write his letters and give them to a person which hee had sent expresly to reliev them; which hee should acknowledg as a favor and correspond accordingly.</p>
            <p>And another of the same King to <hi>Augustino Barbarigo</hi> the Duke, dated 18 Oct. 1487. in the which relating, that hee ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving need of wood for the reparation of a fortress standing in the mouth of <hi>Narenta,</hi> hee praied, that hee might have leav to carry it unto <hi>Segna</hi> by Sea, and that there might bee letters patents made thereof, offering to gratifie him in a greater matter.</p>
            <p>Hee added to this a letter of <hi>Anne</hi> Queen of <hi>Hungarie</hi> 30 Aug. 1502. in the which recounting the sterilitie of the countrie of <hi>Segna,</hi> shee desite's leav to bring certain victuals from <hi>Puglia</hi> and <hi>Marca,</hi> and that hee would give to the bearer, who was sent on purpose, letters of licence for the same, promising to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg it as a great favor and courtesie.</p>
            <p>Lastly hee produced a letter dated 3 Sept. 1504. of <hi>Giovanni de Dura</hi> Captain of <hi>Pismo,</hi> servant to the Emperor <hi>Maximilian,</hi> which hee writ unto the Duke <hi>Leonardo Loredano,</hi> importing, that <hi>Giacomo Croato,</hi> a subject of his Majesties, parting from <hi>Fiano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> entered into the Sea, which is under the Dominion of the Republick, for to go to <hi>Segna,</hi> and was there assailed by an armed bark of Pirates in contempt of the Signorie or Republick, and supplicate's that som order might bee taken therein.</p>
            <p>Upon all which particulars, hee weighed most that which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118667:16"/> ought best to bee considered, having respect to the times, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and qualities of the several Princes, and for greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of their assent, hee remembred the yearly cerimonie used at <hi>Venice;</hi> where the Duke in presence of the Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of other Princes, particularly of his Majesties, did use to espous the Sea, by the casting of a Ring into it, with these words: <hi>Desponsamus te mare in signum veri, &amp; perpetui Dominii:</hi> Wee do marrie the Sea, in sign of our true and perpetual Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over it. Which cerimonie as the foresaid writers do affirm, had beginning when Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third was in <hi>Venice,</hi> notwithstanding they add withal, that it was instituted in sign of the Dominion which the Republick had formerly gotten, <hi>jure belli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the 400 complaints of the Emperors subjects, and to the sentence of <hi>Liesina,</hi> hee answered, giving thanks for the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of them, as a thing brought in much to his favor, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caus the complaints do presuppose the prohibition, and the sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, either condemning or absolving do prove the jurisdiction.</p>
            <p>And to the salt-barks, hee said, that they were not suffered to go to <hi>Venice,</hi> as never any are suffered to go, all forreign salt beeing prohibited to enter into that citie; and if it were not cast into the Sea, it was a courtesie, which ought not to bee imputed to them to their prejudice.</p>
            <p>Hee concluded, that hee had delivered the true sens of the Capitulations, and proved the immemorable possession of the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea; that hee could have said much more, but it seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him superfluous, and these two points were made most clear; <hi>First,</hi> That this pretence of the <hi>Austrians</hi> was but new; and <hi>Secondly,</hi> That their Petition at this Convention could have no place.</p>
            <p>The Imperialists after they had conferred together, took a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118667:17"/> not to persevere in the demand of Justice, and the Baron with <hi>Suorz</hi> said openly, that the <hi>Republick was Patron of the Gulph, and might impose what customs they thought fitting; and that they thought so in their consciences:</hi> but there withall they were of an opinion, that for honestie sake, and for the friendship which the Republick had with the hous of <hi>Austria,</hi> it should bee don with the least incommoditie of the subjects to that hous, as could bee possible. The other three said, that it was now no time, either to approve or to disapprove the Dominion of the Sea, but rather to finde by way of courtesie som kinde of temperature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Republick might receiv the rights belonging thereunto from the <hi>Austrian</hi> subjects sailing those Seas, and on the other side, that such conditions annexed formerly thereunto, might bee taken away, which were incommodious to the <hi>Austrians,</hi> and no waies profitable to the <hi>Venetians.</hi> Whereupon divers waies to effect it were examined, and a conclusion taken to refer all to their several Princes, as it was necessarie to refer all things els; the Commission beeing to bee onely perfected by their ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and so this Convention ended.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>